Guide to the Mr. Lady Archive 1992-2005 MSS 362
© 2012 Fales Library and Special Collections
Mr. Lady Archive
1992-2005
MSS 362
© 2012 Fales Library and Special Collections
3.0 linear feet (2 record cartons, 1 document case, 2 flat boxes, and 1 oversized box.)
Mr. Lady Records was an independent record label founded in 1996 by Tammy Rae Carland and Kaia Wilson with the intention of supporting lesbian and feminist musicians and artists. The collection includes a wide range of material documenting the record label's operations between the years of 1996-2005. This includes press, promotional material, business records, correspondence, photographs, audiovisual material, and more.
Carland, Tammy Rae
Wilson, Kaia
Related Archival Materials note
Provenance
The Mr. Lady Archive was donated to NYU's Fales Library and Special Collections by Tammy Rae Carland, a cofounder of Mr. Lady Records, in 2012.
Scope and Content
The Mr. Lady Archive consists of a wide range of material documenting the operation of the record label between the years of 1996-2005. This includes press, promotional material, business records, correspondence, photographs, audio-visual material, and more. The collection also includes some material that predates the establishment of the label, specifically including press clippings from the Riot Grrrl Movement circa 1992-1996.
This material is divided into eight series:
Series I: Production: This series contains material relating to the production of Mr. Lady merchandise. This specifically includes mock-ups of posters, cover art, and stickers for the label and its artists, particularly Le Tigre.
Series II: Correspondence: The correspondence in this series primarily consists of fan mail.There is also a limited amount of business related correspondence.
Series III: Office Files: This series, in part, consists of business contacts with Mr. Lady's distribution company Mordam. It also contains ephemeral material "from the walls" of Mr. Lady's office.
Series IV: Press: This series includes press generated by the label, Kaia Wilson and Tammy Rae Carland, or the record label's bands.The bulk of this series consists of complete copies of magazines with post-it notes indicating the article's location. (The post-it notes were photocopied and removed during processing. They are now clipped to the back page of each magazine.) The series also contains some clippings detailing Kathleen Hanna's career and involvement in the Riot Grrrl Movement, which predated the foundation of the label.
Series V: Promotional: This series consists of ads, posters, and other promotional material advertising Mr. Lady and its bands.
Series VI: Photographs: This series consists of personal and candid tour photographs.
Series VII: Media: This series includes both audio and visual recordings some of which were commercially released by Mr. Lady. Formats include VHS, DAT, CD, vinyl records, and audio cassette tapes. This series also includes data storage disks.
Subseries A: Video- Originals
Subseries B: Video- Access Copies
Subseries C: Audio- Originals
Subseries D: Audio- Access Copies
Subseries E: Data Storage- Originals
Subseries F: Vinyl Access Copies
Series VIII: Objects: The final series of this collection consists of unique objects. This includes merchandise, such as T-Shirts and a Tote Bag, as well as handmade crafts, including sock puppets of Kaia Wilson and Tammy Rae Carland. There are also some objects (i.e. the miniature replica of the Titanic and a CD opener) that were removed from "Small Stuff from the walls of MLR."
Arrangement
Folders in series I-VI are arranged alphabetically within the series. The Audio and Vinyl Access Copies are kept in their original order by release date.
Biographical/Historical note
Mr. Lady Records (also known as Mr. Lady Records and Videos) was founded in 1996 by Tammy Rae Carland and Kaia Wilson as an independent record label and video art distributor specifically committed to lesbian and feminist cultural productions. Through most of its existence, Mr. Lady Records was located in Durham, North Carolina. The label moved to San Francisco in 2002. Between 1996 and 2005, Mr. Lady released nearly thirty albums and also oversaw the distribution of a dozen video artists. This included the works of Tami Hart, Sarah Dougher, the Butchies, and Le Tigre.
Co-founder Tammy Rae Carland was born in Portland, Maine in 1965. She received her BA from The Evergreen State College and MFA from UC Irvine. While running Mr. Lady, Carland was also employed as an Assistant Professor of Photography at the University of North Carolina, Chapel Hill. In 2002, she accepted a post at California College of the Arts in San Francisco, where she is now an Associate Professor of Fine Arts and Photography and as well as the chair of the Photography Department. Carland primarily works with photography, experimental video, and small-run publications. Her zine I (heart) Amy Carter was influential in the Riot Grrrl Movement of the early 1990s. Kaia Wilson was born in 1974 and is originally from Oregon. Her first band, Adickdid, was formed when she was fifteen years old. She subsequently went on to have a prolific career as a solo artist as well as the frontwoman of queercore punk bands Team Dresch (primarily 1993-1998) and the Butchies (1998-2005). Tammy Rae Carland and Kaia Wilson were partners during the years they ran Mr. Lady together.
Works Cited:
Conditions Governing Access
Open to researchers. Appointments are necessary for the use of manuscript and archival collections.
Audiovisual materials have not been preserved and may not be available to researchers.
Carland, Tammy Rae; Dougher, Sarah, (Vocalist); Fateman, Johanna; Hanna, Kathleen, 1968-; Hart, Tami; Le Tigre (Musical group).; Samson, J.D.; Wilson, Kaia; Audiocassettes.; Business records.; Buttons (information artifacts); CD-Rs.; Clippings (information artifacts); Correspondence.; Ephemera.; Feminism.; Feminist music.; Feminist punk electronic music.; Hard disks.; Independent filmmakers.; Lesbians |z United States.; Magazines (periodicals); Photographs.; Posters.; Press releases.; Punk rock music.; Riot grrrl movement.; San Francisco (Calif.); T-shirts.; Transparencies.; Video art.; Videotapes.; Women rock musicians.; Zines.
- Series I: Production
  Scope and Content
  This series contains material relating to the production of Mr. Lady merchandise. This specifically includes mock-ups of posters, cover art, and stickers for the label and its artists, particularly Le Tigre.
  - [Art Master Le Tigre Poster], [1999] (Box 7, Folder 1)
  - [Le Tigre Transparent Films], undated (Box 7, Folder 2)
  - [Mock ups for Le Tigre cover art—Remixes], 2002 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - [Mock ups for Le Tigre cover art— From the Desk...], 2000-2003 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - [Mock ups for Le Tigre cover art— From the Desk of Mr. Lady], [2001] (Box 7, Folder 3)
  - Mr. Lady catologs, stickers, pins, undated (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Mr. Lady Logo [Transparent] Films, undated (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Mr. Lady Logo [Transparent] Films, undated (Box 7, Folder 4)
  - Random Art Logos, Stickers, Pins, undated (Box 1, Folder 5)
- Series II: Correspondence
  The correspondence in this series primarily consists of fan mail.There is also a limited amount of business related correspondence.
  - [correspondence], undated (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - [correspondence], undated (Box 8, Folder 5)
  - Saved Mail 1 of 2, 1997-2002 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Saved Mail 2 of 2, 1997-2002 (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Saved Mail, 1997-2002 (Box 7, Folder 6)
- Series III: Office Files
  This series, in part, consists of business contacts with Mr. Lady's distribution company Mordam. It also contains ephemeral material "from the walls" of Mr. Lady's office.
  - Business License, 2003-2005 (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - [Ephemera from Mr. Lady Office] 1 of 2, undated (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - [Ephemera from Mr. Lady Office] 2 of 2, undated (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - [Ephemera from the Office of Mr. Lady], undated (Box 7, Folder 7)
  - [Independent Weekly Award for Mr. Lady], 2001 (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - Mordam Contracts, 1999-2003 (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - [Mordam Material in a Michael Jackson Folder], 1999-2001 (Box 1, Folder 14)
  - Small Stuff from the walls of MRL Office NC, undated (Box 1, Folder 15)
- Series IV: Press
  This series includes press generated by the label, Kaia Wilson and Tammy Rae Carland, or the record label's bands.The bulk of this series consists of complete copies of magazines with post-it notes indicating the article's location. (The post-it notes were photocopied and removed during processing. They are now clipped to the back page of each magazine.) The series also contains some clippings detailing Kathleen Hanna's career and involvement in the Riot Grrrl Movement, which predated the foundation of the label.
  - [Advocate Magazine], 1999-2002 (Box 1, Folder 16)
  - Archival Riot Girl, Bikini Kill, Julie Ruin, Kathleen 1 of 3, 1992-2001 (Box 1, Folder 17)
  - Archival Riot Girl, Bikini Kill, Julie Ruin, Kathleen 2 of 3, 1992-2001 (Box 1, Folder 18)
  - Archival Riot Girl, Bikini Kill, Julie Ruin, Kathleen 3 of 3, 1992-2001 (Box 1, Folder 19)
  - Archival Riot Girl, Bikini Kill, Julie Ruin, Kathleen, 1992-2001 (Box 7, Folder 8)
  - [Bitch Magazine] 1 of 2, 1999-2002 (Box 1, Folder 20)
  - [Bitch Magazine] 2 of 2, 1999-2002 (Box 1, Folder 21)
  - [Bust Magazine] 1 of 2, 1999-2002 (Box 1, Folder 22)
  - [Bust Magazine] 2 of 2, 1999-2002 (Box 1, Folder 23)
  - [Catch the Beat Zine], 1999-2000 (Box 1, Folder 24)
  - [Curve Magazine], 2001-2002 (Box 1, Folder 25)
  - [Girlfriends Magazine] 1 of 3, 1998-2002 (Box 1, Folder 26)
  - [Girlfriends Magazine] 2 of 3, 1998-2002 (Box 1, Folder 27)
  - [Girlfriends Magazine] 3 of 3, 1998-2002 (Box 1, Folder 28)
  - [Misc. Magazines] 1 of 4, 1999-2002 (Box 1, Folder 29)
  - [Misc. Magazines] 2 of 4, 1999-2002 (Box 1, Folder 30)
  - [Misc. Magazines] 3 of 4, 1999-2002 (Box 1, Folder 31)
  - [Misc. Magazines] 4 of 4, 1999-2002 (Box 3, Folder 1)
  - [Misc. Magazine], 1999-2002 (Box 7, Folder 9)
  - [Venus Magazine] 1 of 3, 2000-2004 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - [Venus Magazine] 2 of 3, 2000-2004 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - [Venus Magazine] 3 of 3, 2000-2004 (Box 3, Folder 4)
- Series V: Promotional
  This series consists of ads, posters, and other promotional material advertising Mr. Lady and its bands.
  - Ads, 1999-2003 (Box 3, Folder 5)
  - Band Photos, undated (Box 3, Folder 6)
  - Mr. Lady Music Release Posters, undated (Box 3, Folder 7)
  - Mr. Lady Music Release Posters (Box 8, Folder 10)
  - [Mr. Lady Posters], undated (Box 8, Folder 11)
  - Mr Lady Promo, 2000-2003 (Box 3, Folder 8)
  - Mr Lady Promo, 1996-2003 (Box 8, Folder 12)
  - Mr. Lady Show Posters, undated (Box 3, Folder 9)
  - Mr. Lady Show Posters, undated (Box 8, Folder 13)
  - Promo Stuff Misc., 1999-2000 (Box 3, Folder 10)
- Series VI: Photographs
  This series consists of personal and candid tour photographs.
  - Photos Misc. 1 of 3, 1999-2000 (Box 3, Folder 9)
  - Photos Misc. 2 of 3, 1999-2000 (Box 3, Folder 10)
  - Photos Misc. 3 of 3, 1999-2000 (Box 3, Folder 11)
- Series VII: Media
  This series includes both audio and visual recordings some of which were commercially released by Mr. Lady. Formats include VHS, DAT, CD, vinyl records, and audio cassette tapes. This series also includes data storage disks.
  - Subseries A: Video- Originals
    - Cry for Everything..., undated (Box 4, Media ID: 362.0001)
    - Cherry Bomb- Rough Cut '99, 1999 (Box 4, Media ID: 362.0002)
    - Team Dresch MWMF [Michigan Womyn's Musical Festival] 1995 (Box 4, Media ID: 362.0003)
    - Live at [illegible word]- Tami Hart; Butchies 5-28th #2, undated (Box 4, Media ID: 362.0004)
    - Mr. Lady 5 Year Anniversary Show- May 5, 2001- Cat's Cradle (Box 4, Media ID: 362.0005)
    - Rousted From Fireweed- K.M.- RFF- Kelly Marie Martin, undated (Box 4, Media ID: 362.0006)
    - Cecilia Dougherty "Claudia", 1987 (Box 4, Media ID: 362.0007)
    - Motor Baby and Rousted Master- Kelly Martin, undated (Box 4, Media ID: 362.0008)
  - Subseries B: Video- Access Copies
    Conditions Governing Access
    Audiovisual materials have not been preserved and are not currently available to researchers.
  - Subseries C: Audio- Originals
    - The Crowns- 4 Track Demo, undated (Box 4, Media ID: 362.0009)
    - Darien Brahms "St. Joan" Master, 2002 (Box 4, Media ID: 362.0010)
    - Sarah Dougher May 26,2000 Live at Cat's Cradle Carborro, NC (Box 4, Media ID: 362.0012)
    - The Haggard "No Future"- 5/31/01- Mr Lady Records, 2001 (Box 4, Media ID: 362.0013)
    - Calling All... Comp, undated (Box 4, Media ID: 362.0014)
    - Modern Recording- Mr Lady Comp #2- CD ref #4, 2000 (Box 4, Media ID: 362.0015)
    - Tracy and the Plastics "Oh Maria" Recorded by Joe Preston Feb. 2000 Contact: Chainsaw (Box 4, Media ID: 362.0016)
    - Mr Lady Comp set 2 6/2/99, 1999 (Box 4, Media ID: 362.0017)
    - Calling All... Comp, undated (Box 4, Media ID: 362.0018)
    - Mr Lady Comp CD set 2 8/23/00, 2000 (Box 4, Media ID: 362.0019)
    - Un-Mastered Mr. Lady Comp 2000 (Box 4, Media ID: 362.0020)
    - Modern Recording- Mr Lady Compilation- CF set 5 (final), undated (Box 4, Media ID: 362.0021)
    - The Crowns "Shallow End" (Mr. Lady Comp) 24- bit data files (Audio Files) .L, .R, undated (Box 4, Media ID: 362.0022)
    - Kiki & Herb "I'm Not Waiting" (Mr. Lady Comp), undated (Box 4, Media ID: 362.0023)
    - Navy, 2000 (Box 4, Media ID: 362.0024)
    - Darien Brahms 5/2000 (Box 4, Media ID: 362.0025)
    - Shelley Doty- Seems Unlikely (Master), undated (Box 4, Media ID: 362.0026)
    - Lugosi-California Lightening, 1999 (Box 4, Media ID: 362.0027)
    - Origami, undated (Box 4, Media ID: 362.0028)
    - Origami-Measure Up, undated (Box 4, Media ID: 362.0029)
    - Gretchen Phillips- Eau De Lesbianism, 2000 (Box 4, Media ID: 362.0030)
    - Ode to Lesbianism- Gretchen Phillips, undated (Box 4, Media ID: 362.0031)
    - The Kids That Call Us Clowns The Book, 1999 (Box 4, Media ID: 362.0032)
    - Master Tape (Box 4, Media ID: 362.0033)
    - Mixed Down, undated (Box 4, Media ID: 362.0034)
    - [Untitled Tami Hart Cassette Tape- The Kids That Call Us Clowns], undated (Box 4, Media ID: 362.0035)
    - Rubeo, undated (Box 4, Media ID: 362.0036)
    - Tami Hart's Greatest Hits (in bubble wrap even!) Ha Ha..., undated (Box 4, Media ID: 362.0037)
    - Golden Girls- Cued, undated (Box 4, Media ID: 362.0038)
    - Rubeo 7" MRLR- 04, undated (Box 7, Media ID: 362.0039)
    - V For Vendetta- June 12,2000- Sampson (Box 7, Media ID: 362.0040)
    - Sissies- Final Mix, undated (Box 7, Media ID: 362.0041)
    - Rubeo Comp, undated (Box 7, Media ID: 362.0042)
  - Subseries D: Audio- Access Copies
  - Subseries E: Data Storage- Originals
    - MRLR 682 1150 2 of 2, undated (Box 4, Media ID: 362.3.0001)
    - [untitled Mr Lady Disc], undated (Box 4, Media ID: 362.3.0002)
    - V9V Poster, undated (Box 4, Media ID: 362.3.0003)
    - Mr. Lady's, 2000 (Box 4, Media ID: 362.3.0004)
    - MRL Video, undated (Box 4, Media ID: 362.3.0005)
    - MRL Videos Logos Letter Head, undated (Box 4, Media ID: 362.3.0006)
    - V4V CD Tray Folder, undated (Box 4, Media ID: 362.3.0007)
    - MRLR 1 of 2 682 1150, undated (Box 4, Media ID: 362.3.0008)
    - German Mr. Lady Stuff/Misc., undated (Box 4, Media ID: 362.3.0009)
    - MRLR 956 8327 Spring 2001 Catalog and Butchies 3 posters, undated (Box 4, Media ID: 362.3.0010)
    - Le Poster/ Cat., undated (Box 4, Media ID: 362.3.0011)
    - Haggard No Future, undated (Box 4, Media ID: 362.3.0012)
    - Melissa's Zip Disk #2, undated (Box 4, Media ID: 362.3.0013)
    - Mr Lady 682. 1150 Cat. #3, undated (Box 4, Media ID: 362.3.0014)
    - MRLR, undated (Box 4, Media ID: 362.3.0015)
    - MRL Web #2, undated (Box 4, Media ID: 362.3.0016)
    - Mr Lady Catalog Melissa York #2, undated (Box 4, Media ID: 362.3.0017)
    - MRL Web #1, undated (Box 4, Media ID: 362.3.0018)
    - MRLR 956 8327 - Calling All...- MRLR 15 - Tami Hart - MRLR 11, undated (Box 4, Media ID: 362.3.0019)
    - MRLR 06 and 07 Posters (Le Tigre and Butchies), undated (Box 4, Media ID: 362.3.0020)
    - MRLR 12 and 13 posters (Sarah and Haggard), undated (Box 4, Media ID: 362.3.0021)
    - [untitled Mr Lady disc], undated (Box 4, Media ID: 362.3.0023)
    - Dougher, undated (Box 4, Media ID: 362.3.0024)
    - Stills for Mr. Lady K8, undated (Box 4, Media ID: 362.3.0025)
    - TJO Poster, undated (Box 4, Media ID 362.3.0029)
    - TJO/ Le Tigre Poster, undated (Box 4, Media ID: 362.3.0030)
    - MRLR-27 TKO 956 8327, undated (Box 4, Media ID: 362.3.0031)
    - TJO/Le Tigre Poster (Box 4, Media ID: 362.3.0031)
  - Subseries F: Vinyl- Access Copies
- Series VIII: Objects
  This series includes merchandise, such as T-Shirts and a Tote Bag, as well as handmade crafts, including sock puppets of Kaia Wilson and Tammy Rae Carland. There are also some objects (i.e. the miniature replica of the Titanic and a CD opener) that were removed from "Small Stuff from the walls of MLR."
  - Mr. Lady Logo Tote Bag (Box 5, Object ID: 362.2.0001)
  - Mr. Lady Logo T-Shirt (light gray) (Box 5, Object ID: 362.2.0002)
  - Mr. Lady Logo T-Shirt (dark gray) (Box 5, Object 362.2.0003)
  - Butchies T-Shirt (Box 5, Object 362.2.0004)
  - Le Tigre T-Shirt (white on black) (Box 5, Object 362.2.0005)
  - Butchies Logo T-Shirt (red on black) (Box 6, Object 362.2.0006)
  - Mr. Lady Logo T-Shirt (orange on red) (Box 6, Object 362.2.0007)
  - Mr. Lady Logo Stamp (Box 6, Object 362.2.0008)
  - Destination Stamp (Box 6, Object 362.2.0009)
  - Mr. Lady Cat Doll (made by Lake Lloyd), 1999 (Box 6, Object 362.2.0010)
  - Kaia Wilson and Tammy Rae Carland Sock Puppets (Box 6, Object 362.2.0011)
  - Mini Replica of the Titantic (Box 6, Object ID: 362.2.0011)
  - Mordam Records CD Opener (Box 6, Object ID: 362.2.0012)
  - Mr. Lady Records Pens (Box 6, Object 362.2.0014)